in this Tasker session we are going to
talk about the multi-user workspaces in
Tosca now until now we have seen how to
create a single user workspace and how
to use it now this single user workspace
can be used by only one user at a time
right if multiple users want to use the
same workspace you have to create a
multi-user workspace in Tosca now you
might think that multi-user workspace
can only be created if you have got a
database Connection in place but it's
not always true okay so Tosca also
provides you uh with an option where
even if you don't have a particular
database like Oracle or SQL server or
db2 you can still create a in-memory
database
multi-user workspace and that can be
done using uh the sqlite okay so there
is an option to create a multi-user
workspace using sqlite you don't require
any uh connection strings for that
particular database type and you can use
it to create a multi-user workspace to
check out the functionality in Tosca
but one thing you have to remember is
this sqlite workspace cannot be used in
a real-time project okay it can be used
for a demo or practice as I said to
check out the functionality for
multi-user workspace but it is not a
real solution where you can use it for a
real uh project okay for real project
you should have a a dedicated database
instance either Oracle MSS skill server
or a db2 workspace right but uh for
practice we can still use this and that
is what I'm going to show you how you
can create a multi-user workspace and
then probably you can check out all the
functionalities which come up on this
multi-user workspace which is not
available in the single user workspace
okay so the process is almost the same
okay so not much changes if you're not
using a particular database instance
then you don't need to provide the
connection string which contains the
username password and the DB connection
string
but for sqlite workspace if you're
creating that you don't require those
okay
so when you come to the Tosca Commander
screen uh there is a create new Option
okay and until now we have been using
this type of repository as none which
will create a single user workspace but
now we are going to go into the other
option which is sqlite okay as I said if
you have a dedicated database instance
you can use Oracle Ms SQL server and db2
so if you look at the MSS skill server
uh so you will have some additional
fields which you need to fill okay uh
the most important is the connection
string
now uh if you have this connection
string and if you place it here you can
test the connection okay and once the
connection is valid then you can create
your workspace in that particular
database so that is the process okay and
it will be similar for Oracle or db2
okay so any kind of database required
you have to at least give a connection
string now schema is not mandatory it's
an optional field so it's mostly the
connection string and then testing the
connection okay
so uh for sqlite as I said you don't
require the connection string or the
schema right so as you can see those
fields are not available but still it
will create a multi-user workspace for
me okay
uh and that's what I'm going to do okay
so it will create the new workspace in
this folder you can always change this
to any particular folder you have to
give it a name okay
so what I'm going to give is multi demo
okay so this is my uh
multi-user workspace and you can also
create a slim workspace now Slim
workspace will take less amount of space
but uh
if you have got a high data volume right
um
then you should use the slim workspace
which will basically speed up your whole
repository but if not then I prefer not
to use it okay
also if you have not created any other
repository using this particular or any
other workspace using this particular
repository then do remember to check out
the use existing repository otherwise uh
the you cannot proceed okay so let's
check out this and now I can see that it
has been enabled okay
so uh once you have created a particular
workspace using this repository then you
can click on this use existing
Repository
Okay now click on OK
and it will start creating a multi-user
workspace for you
uh once it is created uh it will open
that workspace
and now we can see some of the options
which will be enabled right which were
not present or disabled
um when we are using a single user
workspace okay
also uh one major difference you will
see that for single user workspace there
was never a login screen right but now
you can see that there is a login screen
now if you get this kind of a login
screen when you create a multi-user
workspace for the first time
okay uh you would wonder what is the
password for this workspace but for now
Tosca is created a user for you which is
the admin which is the default user and
there is no password for it okay so
don't enter any password and click on
login
so now you can create different users in
this kind of a workspace also uh when
you go into your project okay so if I
open my project
and I put it here you can see there is a
green sign which is displayed and this
green sign which is displayed for every
particular section or object right
it tells you that these objects are
checked out or the project is even
checked out okay so there is a checkout
and check-in process
which is there for a multi-user
workspace because multiple users are
working on the same workspace so there
has to be a process of how the changes
will get merged right when multiple
users are working in a workspace
so when you create or open a multi-user
workspace right uh the objects which are
checked out uh you can only work on
those particular objects okay now if you
see any particular object uh with red
color in the beginning right a red
stripe then that means that object is
checked out by some other user and you
basically cannot work on that particular
object or on that particular folder
right because somebody else is working
on that so this is how uh the checkout
and check-in process works so if a
particular object or folder has been
checked out by any particular user and
he's working on it no other user can
basically uh make any changes to that
particular folder or object
okay so once you complete working on a
particular folder or object you have to
check in your changes
and if other users are simultaneously
working on other objects or other
folders right and they check in
something then there is an option called
update all right so when you click on
this update all what it will do uh it
will fetch all the changes from the
repository or the database right and it
will merge those changes into your
particular workspace right so you will
get all the changes which has been done
by other users on different objects
right into your repository before you
work right so before you start working
on a multi-user workspace uh you should
always do an update all this process can
also be automated uh using the Tosca TC
shell commands right you can
you can put a file which can update all
the repositories before they you start
working on that okay or else you can
manually come and do it here uh just do
an update all so that it fetches all the
changes from the database uh if multiple
users are working on that okay and uh if
all the objects are checked out by you
then no other user will be able to work
on this so once you finish your work you
should always remember to check in all
which will basically do a check-in of
all your changes right
so there are basically four options when
you are working within a team right so
this section tells you that
so there is uh update all as I said that
is checking all which will check in
everything which has been checked out by
you
okay and then there is a checkout option
and a checkout tree option okay so let's
see what is the difference between a
checkout and a checkout tree option okay
so check out uh basically at uh it is
related to just one single object but
checkout 3 will basically check out all
the objects which are contained inside
that particular folder or uh inside that
particular object right
so if you look uh at any particular
folder right so if I go into this
execution folder
and I right click on this I will also
get this option so either you can check
out from here or you can do a checkout
tree from here okay
now if I do a checkout so if I am doing
this checkout it will basically check
out only the execution folder but it
will not check out the other objects
which are contained inside this
execution folder right
so if you want to work on all the
objects in this particular folder or say
if you are working on a particular test
case folder right so you will what you
will want is you will want to check out
the complete folder because currently
you are working on it and you don't want
anyone else to change that in those kind
of scenarios you should basically do a
checkout tree so that all the objects
are checked out which you are currently
working on and then you can check in all
once you finish working on that okay
so that's how you should be working on
uh see um now if you have not checked
out any particular uh object or folder
like this test cases okay you can see
there is no no option to either create a
folder or a test case template or a test
case right so it is not showing any
options and that's what happens when you
work in a multi-user workspace you have
to first check out that particular
object which is the test cases folder
and when I right click on this now I get
all the options right so I can create a
folder I can create a test case right
so if I create a
test case folder like this right and
then I create some test cases here okay
and maybe another test case
so I have got these many test cases
inside this folder right and now I do a
check in all and it will basically check
in everything inside my repository right
so the execution folder was checked in
the test cases folder were checked in
okay
now if I want to work on this folder in
test case 0 1 and I don't want anyone
else to make changes to this because I
expect a lot of changes in all the
different objects okay so in that kind
of a scenario I can do a checkout tree
right so if I do a checkout tree uh all
the objects inside this folder will be
checked out and uh nobody else can
basically do any changes on this right
and once I finish this I can do a
check-in all which will basically
check in everything which I have changed
in my workspace and then other users can
access these changes okay
so as you can see
this is basically a check-in checkout
process it is pretty much similar to any
code repository if you have worked on
get or GitHub uh you will also follow
this check-in and checkout process where
you check out your code changes and you
do the code changes and then you check
in uh into the repositories so that
other developers can or other testers
can basically access those changes right
and if that is in conflicts then you
have to resolve that conflicts and you
have to merge your changes with other
developers so it's a similar process
here in Tosca as well right there is
basically just one difference is that uh
whenever you are working on a particular
object it doesn't give access to other
developers they have to wait until you
check in right so it's very important
that once you are completed with your
work you do a check in all and before
you start working you do a update all so
that you get all the changes so it's
pretty simplified so that uh if many
users are working in a multi-user
workspace they don't get many conflicts
and you don't have to spend time on
resolving those conflicts and doing a
merge right so Tosca simplifies this
process it's just just every user will
work on its own objects and then once
they check in all or update all those
changes will be merged and available for
everyone okay
so this is one aspect of multi-user
workspace when you work on a real-time
project you have to follow this process
of check-in and checkout and also the
update all